Tristan RH Goodbody

POST-DOCTORAL FELLOW

University of British Columbia, Vancouver

Passionate about enhancing forest management knowledge and practices. Advocates for the incorporation of multi-scale remote sensing technologies to improve forest inventory frameworks. Primary research interests include digital aerial photogrammetry, lidar, remotely piloted aircraft and their application to forest inventory and management fromeworks.

Technical Skills_____

Project Management	Technical Writing	Data Analytics
Effective Planning, Organization,	Publications, Official Reports,	R, Management, Manipulation,
Communication, Implementation	Funding Grants	Visualization, Interpretation

Experience _____

Post-Doctoral Fellow Vancouver, BC

FACULTY OF FOREST RESOURCES MANAGEMENT (UBC)

June 2019 - Present

- · Assessment of wood attributes using remote sensing (AWARE) & Canadian Wood Fibre Center Forest Innovation Program.
 - Mentor graduate students on remote sensing practices and routines
 - Developed lidar processing and analysis frameworks to enhance forest inventory knowledge
 - Developed a structurally guided sampling package sgsR
 - Collaborated with international govnerment, industry, and academic partners

Teaching assistant Vancouver, BC

FACULTY OF FOREST RESOURCES MANAGEMENT (UBC)

May 2015 - March 2019

- Leading & superving applied exercises to guide student knowledge of remote sensing concepts.
 - Guiding students to success in written and oral submissions
 - FRST 443 Remote sensing for ecosystem management (Undergraduate)
 - FRST 521 Advanced earth observation and image processing (Graduate)
 - Held weekly office hours, guest lectured, developed and graded assignments and research proposals

Planning Forester Intern - Co-op

Chetwynd, BC

CHETWYND FOREST INDUSTRIES - WEST FRASER MILLS LTD.

May 2014 - December 2014

- Working in a team and individually to implement West Fraser Management objectives.
 - Site plan preparation
 - Harvest planning & layout
 - Silviculture assessments and reforestation quality inspections
 - post-fire salvage planning and management
 - GIS management
 - Forest appraisals

Planning Forester Intern - Co-op

Williams Lake, BC

May 2013 - September 2013

ALEX FRASER RESEARCH FOREST (UBC)

- Implemented planning and management perscriptions.
 - Road & timber layout
 - Timber cruising
 - Volume determination
 - Avian habitat assessments

Education

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, BC

PHD REMOTE SENSING OF FORESTS

May 2015 - March 2019

· Assessing the role of digital aerial photogrammetry for characterizing forest structure and enhancing forest inventories

DECEMBER 2021 TRISTAN RH GOODBODY · CV

University of British Columbia

September 2010 - January 2015

Vancouver, BC

BSc Natural Resources Conservation (Hons.& Co-op)

- · Science and Management Major.
 - Cons 330: Conservation Policy
 - FRST 443: Remote Sensing Of Ecosystem Management
 - CONS 451: Integrated Field School

Awards.

PhD Funding Vancouver, BC

NSERC PGSD 2018

PhD Funding
HARRY G. SMITH SCHOLARSHIP
2018

Peer-Reviewed Publications

- 1. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Srivastava, V., Parsons, B., Kearney, S. P., Rickbeil, G. J., & Stenhouse, G. B. (2021). Mapping recreation and tourism use across grizzly bear recovery areas using social network data and maximum entropy modelling. *Ecological Modelling*, 440, 109377.
- 2. Toit, F. du, Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Stoehr, M., & El-Kassaby, Y. A. (2021). Deriving internal crown geometric features of douglas-fir from airborne laser scanning in a realized-gain trial. *Forestry: An International Journal of Forest Research*, 94(3), 442–454.
- 3. Fu, X., Zhang, Z., Cao, L., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Liu, H., Shen, X., & Wu, X. (2021). Assessment of approaches for monitoring forest structure dynamics using bi-temporal digital aerial photogrammetry point clouds. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 255, 112300.
- 4. Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Goodbody, T. R., Hennigar, C. R., Wulder, M. A., Socha, J., & Woods, M. E. (2021). Estimating changes in forest attributes and enhancing growth projections: A review of existing approaches and future directions using airborne 3D point cloud data (feb, 10.1007/s40725-021-00135-w, 2021). *Current Forestry Reports*, 7(1), 25–30.
- 5. Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Goodbody, T. R., Hennigar, C. R., Wulder, M. A., Socha, J., & Woods, M. E. (2021). Publisher correction: Estimating changes in forest attributes and enhancing growth projections: A review of existing approaches and future directions using airborne 3D point cloud data. *Current Forestry Reports*, 1–6.
- 6. Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., Queinnec, M., Luther, J. E., Bolton, D. K., White, J. C., Wulder, M. A., Lier, O. R. van, & Hermosilla, T. (2021). Modelling lidar-derived estimates of forest attributes over space and time: A review of approaches and future trends. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 260, 112477.
- 7. Kearney, S. P., Larsen, T. A., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., & Stenhouse, G. B. (2021). Characterizing off-highway road use with remote-sensing, social media and crowd-sourced data: An application to grizzly bear (ursus arctos) habitat. *Remote Sensing*, 13(13), 2547.
- 8. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Luther, J. E., Tompalski, P., Mulverhill, C., Frizzle, C., Fournier, R., Furze, S., & Herniman, S. (2021). Airborne laser scanning for quantifying criteria and indicators of sustainable forest management in canada. *Canadian Journal of Forest Research*, *51*(7), 972–985.
- 9. Coops, N. C., Achim, A., Arp, P., Bater, C. W., Caspersen, J. P., Cote, J.-F., Dech, J. P., Dick, A. R., Ewijk, K. van, Fournier, R., & others. (2021). Advances in the application of remote sensing for forest information needs in canada: Lessons learned from a national collaboration of academic, industry, and government stakeholders. *Forestry Chronicle*, 97(2), 127–147.
- 10. Goodbody, T. R., White, J. C., Coops, N. C., & LeBoeuf, A. (2021). Benchmarking acquisition parameters for digital aerial photogrammetric data for forest inventory applications: Impacts of image overlap and resolution. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 265, 112677.
- 11. Czekajlo, A., Coops, N. C., & Goodbody, T. R. (2021). Untangling the effect of urban vegetation type and structure on spectrally unmixed greenness. *Remote Sensing Letters*, *12*(12), 1216–1226.

- 12. Achim, A., Moreau, G., Coops, N. C., Axelson, J. N., Barrette, J., Bédard, S., Byrne, K. E., Caspersen, J., Dick, A. R., D'Orangeville, L., & others. (2021). The changing culture of silviculture. *Forestry: An International Journal of Forest Research*, cpab047.
- 13. Toit, F. du, Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., El-Kassaby, Y. A., Stoehr, M., Turner, D., & Lucieer, A. (2020). Characterizing variations in growth characteristics between douglas-fir with different genetic gain levels using airborne laser scanning. *Trees*, *34*(3), 649–664.
- 14. Goodbody, T. R., Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Wulder, M. A., & Sanelli, M. (2020). Uncovering spatial and ecological variability in gap size frequency distributions in the canadian boreal forest. *Scientific Reports*, 10(1), 1–12.
- 15. Xu, Z., Shen, X., Cao, L., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Zhong, T., Zhao, W., Sun, Q., Ba, S., Zhang, Z., & others. (2020). Tree species classification using UAS-based digital aerial photogrammetry point clouds and multispectral imageries in subtropical natural forests. *International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation*, 92, 102173.
- 16. Goodbody, T. R., Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., Hopkinson, C., Treitz, P., & Ewijk, K. van. (2020). Forest inventory and diversity attribute modelling using structural and intensity metrics from multi-spectral airborne laser scanning data. *Remote Sensing*, 12(13), 2109.
- 17. Roussel, J.-R., Auty, D., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., Meador, A. S., Bourdon, J.-F., Boissieu, F. de, & Achim, A. (2020). lidR: An r package for analysis of airborne laser scanning (ALS) data. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 251, 112061.
- 18. Chadwick, A. J., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hervieux, A., Bater, C. W., Martens, L. A., White, B., & Röeser, D. (2020). Automatic delineation and height measurement of regenerating conifer crowns under leaf-off conditions using UAV imagery. *Remote Sensing*, *12*(24), 4104.
- 19. Gómez, C., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Álvarez-Taboada, F., & Sanz-Ablanedo, E. (2020). Forest ecosystem monitoring using unmanned aerial systems. In *Unmanned aerial remote sensing* (pp. 173–196). CRC Press.
- 20. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., & White, J. C. (2019). Digital aerial photogrammetry for updating area-based forest inventories: A review of opportunities, challenges, and future directions. *Current Forestry Reports*, 5(2), 55–75.
- 21. Goodbody, T. R. H. (2019). Assessing the role of digital aerial photogrammetry for characterizing forest structure and enhancing forest inventories [PhD thesis]. University of British Columbia.
- 22. Nuijten, R. J., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., & Pelletier, G. (2019). Examining the multi-seasonal consistency of individual tree segmentation on deciduous stands using digital aerial photogrammetry (DAP) and unmanned aerial systems (UAS). *Remote Sensing*, 11(7), 739.
- 23. Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., & Cao, L. (2019). *Four steps to extend drone use in research*. Nature Publishing Group.
- 24. Yancho, J. M. M., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., & Plowright, A. (2019). Fine-scale spatial and spectral clustering of UAV-acquired digital aerial photogrammetric (DAP) point clouds for individual tree crown detection and segmentation. *Ieee Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*, *12*(10), 4131–4148.
- 25. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., & Crawford, P. (2018). Assessing the status of forest regeneration using digital aerial photogrammetry and unmanned aerial systems. *International Journal of Remote Sensing*, 39(15-16), 5246–5264.
- 26. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., McCartney, G., & MacLean, D. A. (2018). Digital aerial photogrammetry for assessing cumulative spruce budworm defoliation and enhancing forest inventories at a landscape-level. *Isprs Journal of Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing*, 142, 1–11.
- 27. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., & Pelletier, G. (2018). Vegetation phenology driving error variation in digital aerial photogrammetrically derived terrain models. *Remote Sensing*, *10*(10), 1554.
- 28. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Crawford, P., & Day, K. J. (2017). Updating residual stem volume estimates using ALS-and UAV-acquired stereo-photogrammetric point clouds. *International Journal of Remote Sensing*, 38(8-10), 2938–2953.

29. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Marshall, P. L., Tompalski, P., & Crawford, P. (2017). Unmanned aerial systems for precision forest inventory purposes: A review and case study. *The Forestry Chronicle*, 93(1), 71–81.

Presentations

AWARE E-lecture Series	Online
DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRIC APPLICATIONS TO ENHANCED FOREST INVENTORY	October 2019
Silvilaser	Foz de Iguazu, Brazil
Uncovering spatial and ecological variability in gap size frequency distributions in the Canadian Boreal forest	October 2019
CIF-IFC Workshop	Edmonton, AB
Examining potential applications of UAS/UAV€™S and digital photogrammetry for various forest management	April 2019
PURPOSES	April 2019
FRI Forest Practitioners Conference	Edmonton, AB
Assessing the status of forest regeneration using digital aerial photogrammetry and unmanned aerial systems	October 2018
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Kamloops, BC
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	February 2018
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Huntsville, ON
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	October 2017
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Kapuskasing, ON
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	October 2017
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Quesnel, BC
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	October 2017
Silvilaser	Blacksburg, USA
Assessing the capacity of DAP to enhance inventory knowledge of Spruce Budworm affected forests	November 2017
Symposium on Systems and Analysis in Forest Resources	Suquamish, USA
UPDATING AIRBORNE LASER SCANNING EFI METRICS USING UAV ACQUIRED DAP POINT CLOUDS	August 2017
UAV and Remote Sensing Workshop	Nanjing, China
UAV AND DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY FOR FORESTRY PURPOSES	July 2017
Assessment of Wood Attributes for Remote Sensing AGM	Edmunston, NB
Assessing the capacity of DAP to enhance inventory knowledge of Spruce Budworm affected forests	May 2017
ForestSAT	Santiago, Chile
MODELLING RESIDUAL STAND VOLUME USING UNMANNED AERIAL VEHICLES AND DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY	November 2016
FP Innovations UAV Workshop	Courtney, BC
UAVs and the University of British Columbia	October 2016
Canadian Remote Sensing Symposium	Winnepeg, MB
MODELLING RESIDUAL STAND VOLUME USING UNMANNED AERIAL VEHICLES AND DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY	June 2016
Southern Interior Silviculture Committee	Kamloops, BC
DAP POINT CLOUDS ACQUIRED FROM UNMANNED AERIAL SYSTEMS (UAS) FOR ENHANCING FOREST INVENTORIES	February 2016
Alex Fraser Research Forest Proof of Concept Workshop	Williams Lake, BC

June 2015

RESEARCH IN USE OF DRONES TO UPDATE LIDAR FOREST INVENTORIES. LIDAR HIGH RESOLUTION INVENTORY FOR THE IDF